<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Question 3</title>
        <author ref="#Durandus">Durandus</author>
        <respStmt>
          <name ref="#jeffreycwitt">Jeffrey C. Witt</name>
          <resp>Transcription Editor</resp>
          <resp>TEI Encoder</resp>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition n="0.0.0-dev">
          <title>Question 3</title>
          <date when="2025-12-12">December 12, 2025</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority>SCTA</authority>
        <availability status="free">
          <p>
            Published under a 
            <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0)</ref>
          </p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <listWit>
          <witness xml:id="L" n="cod-du87us">Lyon 1563</witness>
        </listWit>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <schemaRef n="lbp-diplomatic-1.0.0" url="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng"/>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>
          Encoding of this text has followed the recommendations of the LombardPress 1.0.0
          guidelines for a diplomatic edition.
        </p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <revisionDesc status="draft">
      <listChange>
        <change when="2025-12-12" status="draft" n="0.0.0">
          <p>Created file for the first time.</p>
        </change>
      </listChange>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="en">
    <front>
      <div xml:id="starts-on">
        <pb ed="#L" n="178-r"/>
        <cb ed="#L" n="a"/>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <div xml:id="jsnvu6-e146938"><!-- l2d44q3 -->
        <head xml:id="jsnvu6-e146938-Hd1e101">Question 3</head>
        <head xml:id="jsnvu6-e146938-Hd1e103" type="question-title">
          Whether Christians are bound to obey secular princes
        </head>
        <p xml:id="jsnvu6-e146938-d1e106">
          <cb ed="#L" n="b"/>
          QUESTION THREE
          Whether Christians are bound to obey 
          secular princes
          <!--Thomas 22 q. 10. art. 10 -->
        </p>
        <p xml:id="jsnvu6-e146938-d1e124">
          THIRD, 
          it is asked whether Christians are bound 
          to obey secular princes,
        </p>
        <p xml:id="jsnvu6-e146938-d1e133">
          and it seems that they are not 
          because 
          <ref xml:id="jsnvu6-e146938-Rd1e137">James 1</ref> 
          the evangelical law is called 
          <quote xml:id="jsnvu6-e146938-Qd1e139" source="http://scta.info/resource/iac1_25@5-7">
            the law of perfect 
            liberty
          </quote>,
          which would not be the case, 
          unless it freed them from obedience 
          to any secular prince, 
          therefore, etc. 
        </p>
        <p xml:id="jsnvu6-e146938-d1e137">
          Likewise anyone can lawfully resort to the judgment of one to whom he
          is bound to obey, 
          but it is not lawful for Christians to resort to the judgment of
          secular princes especially if they are unbelievers. 
          Whence 
          <ref xml:id="jsnvu6-e146938-Rd1e161">
            the Apostle 
            reproves in I Corinthians 6
          </ref> 
          certain ones who resorted to judges 
          who were secular unbelievers, 
          therefore it seems that Christians are not bound 
          to obey secular princes, 
          especially if they are unbelievers. 
        </p>
        <p xml:id="jsnvu6-e146938-d1e156">
          ON THE CONTRARY is what 
          <ref xml:id="jsnvu6-e146938-Rd1e178">
            the Apostle says in 
            Romans 13
          </ref> 
          that 
          <quote xml:id="jsnvu6-e146938-Qd1e183" source="http://scta.info/resource/rom13_1@1-6">
            every soul should be subject to the higher powers
          </quote>,
          and that he speaks of secular power, 
          is clear from what 
          is added: 
          for he does not bear the sword in vain. 
          But it is established 
          that he speaks to Christians; 
          to whom he also writes, 
          therefore Christians 
          are bound to obey secular power. 
        </p>
        <p xml:id="jsnvu6-e146938-d1e174">
          RESPONSE. 
          Among secular princes some are 
          believers, 
          and some are unbelievers, 
          and the question will be addressed in both cases 
          using one general principle known in itself, 
          namely this, 
          that if 
          a Christian is legitimately subject to secular power certainly he is bound 
          to obey in those matters to which the power extends not only for 
          the sake of wrath, 
          that is, 
          fear of punishment, 
          but for the sake of conscience, 
          because by not 
          obeying 
          <quote xml:id="jsnvu6-e146938-Qd1e214" source="http://scta.info/resource/rom13_2@5-7">
            he resists the ordinance of God
          </quote>,
          as is said 
          <ref xml:id="jsnvu6-e146938-Rd1e217">
            in Romans 13
          </ref>.
          First 
          therefore it will be shown that Christians are legitimately subject to 
          believing secular power. 
          And second it will be inquired whether they are legitimately subject to
          unbelieving secular power. 
        </p>
        <p xml:id="jsnvu6-e146938-d1e200">
          The first is clear in two ways: 
          first thus, 
          that which is according to 
          the dictate of right reason is not removed by faith and grace, 
          for faith 
          and grace do not destroy nature or natural reason, 
          but perfect them, 
          but secular authority ought according to the dictate 
          of right reason to exist among men, 
          as is clear from the preceding question, 
          therefore this is not removed from Christians by faith and grace, 
          by which 
          they are distinguished from others. 
          Likewise wherever the order 
          of justice can be disturbed, 
          it is fitting that there be some who by their office make this order 
          to be observed, 
          but among Christians the order of 
          justice happens to be disturbed, 
          not only in spiritual matters, 
          but also in temporal matters, 
          therefore 
          it is fitting that there be some who by their office make this order to be observed 
          among Christians, 
          but one has this by office only if he who 
          presides, 
          whence 
          <ref xml:id="jsnvu6-e146938-Rd1e258">
            in Romans 13
          </ref> 
          <quote xml:id="jsnvu6-e146938-Qd1e260" source="http://scta.info/resource/rom13_3@10-21">
            Do you wish not to fear the power, 
            do good, 
            and you 
            will have praise from it
          </quote>.
          But if you do evil, 
          fear: 
          for he does not bear the sword in vain, 
          for he is a minister of God, 
          etc. 
          Therefore it is fitting according to 
          right reason, 
          that among Christians there be some who preside not 
          only in spiritual matters (such as ecclesiastical prelates) but also in 
          temporal matters, 
          and these are secular princes. 
          It is clear therefore that secular power 
          among Christians is legitimate, 
          to which subjects are bound to 
          obey in those things which pertain to the right of such power. 
        </p>
        <p xml:id="jsnvu6-e146938-d1e248">
          As for the second question whether an unbelieving secular prince 
          can rightly preside over believing Christians, 
          and consequently whether Christians 
          ought to obey him. 
          A distinction must be made because the dominion or 
          relation of an unbelieving prince over a Christian either preexists the
          distinction between them by faith and unbelief, 
          for instance, 
          because the 
          subject was converted to the faith and not the prince, 
          as in the primitive 
          church commonly happened, 
          or a slave is converted and not the master, 
          as still sometimes happens with slaves of Jews, 
          or such 
          authority or dominion is newly introduced. 
          In the first case some say 
          that the distinction of believers from unbelievers does not remove ipso facto 
          the preceding authority or dominion of unbelievers over believers. 
          The reason for this is, 
          because divine right which is from grace does not remove 
          human right which is from natural reason, 
          but authority 
          was introduced by human right and rests on natural reason, 
          as was shown 
          above. 
          But the distinction of believers from unbelievers is from divine right, 
          therefore this distinction does not remove the preceding authority, 
          or 
          dominion ipso facto, 
          indeed believing subjects are still bound to
          obey unbelieving princes or masters, 
          but they add that 
          although ipso facto such domination is not removed, 
          it can however justly be 
          removed by the ordinance of the church, 
          which has the authority of God,
          because unbelievers by merit of their unbelief deserve to lose 
          power over believers who are transferred into the sons of God, 
          and this indeed 
          the church sometimes does, 
          and sometimes does not do. 
          In 
          those unbelievers who temporally are subject to the church, 
          and 
          in its members this right the church establishes, 
          so that the slave of Jews 
          made a Christian is immediately freed from servitude if he was 
          a home-born slave, 
          that is, 
          born in servitude, 
          and similarly if he was bought for 
          servitude. 
          But if he was bought for trade he is required 
          to be offered for sale within three months, 
          as is clear 
          <ref xml:id="jsnvu6-e146938-Rd1e344">
            57 dist. 
            <pb ed="#L" n="178-v"/>
            <cb ed="#L" n="a"/>
            fraternitatem
          </ref> 
          and 
          <ref xml:id="jsnvu6-e146938-Rd1e355" target="http://scta.info/resource/cice-l5t6-d1e119">
            extra de Iudaeis et Sara. cap. 1
          </ref> 
          and 
          <ref xml:id="jsnvu6-e146938-Rd1e358" target="http://scta.info/resource/cice-l5t6-d1e392">
            the last
          </ref>,
          nor 
          in this does the church do them injury, 
          because since Jews are servants of the 
          church, 
          it can dispose of their goods, 
          just as also 
          secular princes have issued many laws toward their subjects in 
          favor of liberty. 
          But in those unbelievers who temporally 
          are not subject to the church or its members the aforesaid right it does not 
          establish, 
          although it could justly establish it, 
          and this it does to 
          avoid scandal just as also the Lord 
          <ref xml:id="jsnvu6-e146938-Rd1e376" target="http://scta.info/resource/mt17_25 http://scta.info/resource/mt17_26">
            in Matthew 17
          </ref> 
          showed that he 
          could excuse himself from tribute, 
          because the sons are free, 
          but he commanded the tribute 
          to be paid to avoid scandal. 
          
        </p>
        <p xml:id="jsnvu6-e146938-d1e341">
          But I consider the first of these absolutely true, 
          namely that 
          a subject of an unbelieving prince if he is converted to the faith is not ipso 
          facto absolved from the dominion of another, 
          but what is added, 
          that 
          justly by the ordinance of the church having the authority of God he 
          can be absolved, 
          because unbelievers by merit of their unbelief can justly 
          be deprived of the power which they have over believers is indeed true, 
          provided however that something is added namely this that if the prince or 
          unbelieving master not content with his legitimate authority strives 
          to reduce his subject or slave made a Christian to 
          unbelief, 
          nor allows him to be quiet as before, 
          but harasses him 
          by insults offered to the creator then ipso facto he is deprived or at 
          least can be deprived by the authority of the church of the right which he had 
          over his subject. 
        </p>
        <p xml:id="jsnvu6-e146938-d1e372">
          This is clear by reason and by analogy. 
          The reason is as follows: 
          an 
          inferior lord procuring and persuading secession from the 
          superior lord from whom he has all authority to rule is deprived 
          ipso facto or justly deserves to be deprived of the authority of his principate 
          or dominion, 
          but an unbelieving prince or master who 
          strives to recall to unbelief his subject or slave made a Christian 
          and to harass him by insults offered to the creator is 
          of this kind, 
          for he urges secession from God from whom all power comes 
          as is said 
          <ref xml:id="jsnvu6-e146938-Rd1e439" target="http://scta.info/resource/rom13_1">
            in Romans thirteen
          </ref>,
          therefore such a one justly deserves 
          to be deprived of the authority of his dominion. 
          The same is clear by analogy, 
          for equally 
          great is the obligation of spouses to each other as is that of a 
          subject to a prince or slave to a master, 
          but if one of the spouses 
          is converted to the faith while the other remains in unbelief if the 
          unbeliever does not wish to remain with the believer except by drawing him to 
          unbelief, 
          or with blasphemy of the creator, 
          the believer is absolved from the 
          bond by which he was bound to him, 
          in the same way if an unbelieving prince or master 
          strives to reduce a slave or subject made a Christian to 
          unbelief by blaspheming the creator, 
          he deserves to 
          lose the right of dominion which he has over him, 
          whence also in this case 
          Christians move by authority of the church a just war against 
          unbelievers lest they impede the faith of Christ by blasphemies or evil persuasions 
          or manifest persecutions, 
          and perhaps this cause 
          the church has, 
          even now and has long had with respect to anyone converted to 
          the faith with respect to any unbelieving prince or master whether 
          Saracen or Jew, 
          because since they are obstinate in their unbelief it is 
          probable, 
          and has been found by many experiments that 
          any subject or slave of theirs converted to the faith 
          they would strive to reduce to unbelief and therefore this condition is 
          held by the church as fulfilled 
        </p>
        <p xml:id="jsnvu6-e146938-d1e441">
          But if an unbelieving prince or master were content with his 
          legitimate authority, 
          nor would strive to reduce his subject to unbelief, 
          nor bring blasphemies against the creator, 
          but would permit him 
          to be quiet as before, 
          it does not so evidently appear that such 
          a prince ought justly to be deprived of the authority and dominion which he previously 
          had over his subject, 
          because if a subject is newly converted to 
          the faith and not the master, 
          in this there is no new sin of the 
          master, 
          but it is the merit of the subject, 
          therefore the unbelief of the master cannot 
          be a sufficient reason why he should deserve to lose the dominion 
          which he previously legitimately had while existing in the same unbelief, 
          but if 
          there is any reason it ought to be taken from the merit of the slave or subject, 
          who 
          has been newly transferred into the society of the sons of God. 
          And for this reason it could 
          seem to someone that such a one deserves to be absolved from the dominion of the unbelieving prince, 
          and the church by the authority of God could justly absolve him. 
          But although one converted to the faith deserves something greater than such 
          liberty (for he is freed from sin and deserves eternal life) 
          nevertheless it is not necessary that he deserve to be freed from subjection to the 
          unbelieving prince, 
          because one converted to the faith by this alone does not deserve 
          to be freed from that which in no way prejudices the faith, 
          but to be subject to an unbelieving 
          prince who is content with his legitimate authority, 
          nor 
          strives to reduce his subject converted to the faith to unbelief, 
          nor harasses him by any insult offered to the creator, 
          but allows him to be quiet as before, 
          does not prejudice, 
          nor in any way 
          derogate from the faith, 
          therefore from conversion to the faith alone one does not deserve 
          to be absolved from such subjection. 
          The church also although it has on 
          earth the authority of God, 
          that authority however does not exceed the limitation of 
          Scripture. 
          But Scripture expressly states that those converted to the faith ought to be subject 
          to their former masters, 
          although unbelievers, 
          and to 
          obey them. 
          For 
          <ref xml:id="jsnvu6-e146938-Rd1e552">
            the Apostle says in Romans thirteen
          </ref> 
          that the 
          princes who at that time were only unbelievers are ministers of God 
          <cb ed="#L" n="b"/>
          serving for the praise of the good and vengeance of evildoers, 
          for 
          which reason tributes are given to them, 
          and he concludes, 
          <quote xml:id="jsnvu6-e146938-Qd1e561" source="http://scta.info/resource/rom13_7@1-9">
            render therefore to 
            all their dues: 
            to whom tribute is due, 
            tribute; 
            to whom custom is due, 
            custom
          </quote>,
          whence 
          it is clear that he commands those converted to the faith still to be subject to 
          unbelieving princes and to render those things which by reason of subjection are 
          due to them: 
          and 
          <ref xml:id="jsnvu6-e146938-Rd1e573">
            in the second chapter of First Peter
          </ref> 
          it is said, 
          <quote xml:id="jsnvu6-e146938-Qd1e575" source="http://scta.info/resource/Ipetr2_13@1-11 http://scta.info/resource/Ipetr2_14@1-12">
            be subject 
            whether to the king, 
            as excelling, 
            or to governors as sent by him 
            for the punishment of evildoers, 
            and the praise of the good
          </quote>,
          because 
          so is the will of God: 
          and 
          <ref xml:id="jsnvu6-e146938-Rd1e585">
            in the sixth chapter of First Timothy
          </ref> 
          it is said thus 
          <quote xml:id="jsnvu6-e146938-Qd1e588" source="http://scta.info/resource/Itim6_1@1-11">
            whosoever are under the yoke as slaves, 
            let them count their masters worthy of all honor
          </quote>,
          and he speaks of unbelieving masters, 
          as is clear 
          from what is immediately added there. 
          From which it is clear that 
          Scripture does not suggest that slaves or subjects converted to the faith 
          can or ought by the merit alone of their conversion to be absolved from the 
          power of their masters, 
          although unbelievers: 
          indeed it rather seems to 
          insinuate the opposite 
        </p>
        <p xml:id="jsnvu6-e146938-d1e548">
          
          Second this is urged thus, 
          it is illicit that 
          unbelievers who never received the faith should be compelled to the faith, 
          but if 
          the church would deprive an unbelieving prince of his right which he has over 
          his subjects when they are converted to the faith, 
          then it would compel them to the 
          faith by the loss of their goods, 
          because a slave is the property 
          of his master, 
          and every subject is in some way bound to his lord, 
          this the master would lose, 
          unless he were converted to the faith, 
          just as the slaves 
          or subjects, 
          therefore it is illicit to do this: 
          but no 
          power exists for illicit things, 
          therefore, 
          etc. 
        </p>
        <p xml:id="jsnvu6-e146938-d1e572">
          
          Third thus, 
          if one of the spouses is converted to the faith while the other 
          remains in unbelief, 
          if the unbeliever consents to dwell with the believer 
          without drawing him to unbelief; 
          and without 
          blasphemy of the creator the bond 
          of matrimony between them is not dissolved, 
          nor ought to be dissolved, 
          therefore similarly if an unbelieving prince or master 
          requires from a subject or slave made a Christian only that which 
          pertains to the right of his dominion, 
          nor strives to draw him 
          to unbelief, 
          nor harasses him by blasphemies offered to the creator, 
          the obligation which previously existed of the slave 
          to his master or of the subject to his prince is not dissolved, 
          nor can it justly be dissolved. 
          However as was said before, 
          the aforesaid condition perhaps at present 
          does not hold, 
          nor has it long held because of the obstinacy 
          of unbelievers, 
          because of which they strive to blaspheme the creator, 
          and 
          to reduce believers to unbelief, 
          for which reason it is prohibited 
          for a spouse converted to the faith to remain with one who 
          remains in unbelief, 
          as is stated 
          <ref xml:id="jsnvu6-e146938-Rd1e674">
            in the twenty-sixth question 1. 
            chapter on the 
            Jew at the end
          </ref>: 
          and 
          <ref xml:id="jsnvu6-e146938-Rd1e679" target="http://scta.info/resource/gd-p2c28q1-d1e300">
            chapter saepe malorum consortia
          </ref>,
          and in many other places. 
          And therefore the aforesaid condition is now held as null and the opposite is 
          supposed as fulfilled: 
          for which reason the doctors say that 
          a slave or subject converted to the faith can by the church be 
          absolved from the dominion and power of an unbelieving prince. 
          But I think that 
          this is on the supposition of the condition stated above. 
          Thus therefore it is clear 
          how Christians are bound to obey unbelieving masters, 
          when the dominion preexists the distinction between them by faith and 
          unbelief. 
        </p>
        <p xml:id="jsnvu6-e146938-d1e631">
          
          But concerning the authority of unbelievers newly to be introduced 
          over believers in no way does the church permit that unbelievers 
          acquire dominion over believers, 
          or that they be placed over them in any office, 
          and reasonably so. 
          For this tends to scandal and 
          danger to the faith: 
          for easily those who are subjected to the jurisdiction of others 
          are changed by it, 
          as is clear in the books of Kings in many places. 
          For unbelievers despise the faith when they recognize the defects 
          of believers, 
          because of which the church prohibits that such dominion 
          be introduced, 
          but if it has been introduced, 
          as certain 
          Christian princes make from Jews certain overseers and 
          bailiffs, 
          they sin indeed by acting against the statute of the church. 
          But subjects are nevertheless bound to obey Jews thus appointed in those things which 
          pertain to the just execution of the office committed to them. 
        </p>
        <p xml:id="jsnvu6-e146938-d1e664">
          <ref xml:id="jsnvu6-e146938-Rd1e729" target="http://scta.info/resource/jsnvu6-e146938-d1e133">
            TO THE FIRST argument to the contrary
          </ref> 
          it must be said 
          that the evangelical law is called the law of perfect liberty because it 
          frees from the servitude of sin, 
          which is the worst servitude, 
          and from every old law 
          which scarcely anyone could ever bear: 
          and not because it 
          frees from civil servitude by which a subject is bound to obey his 
          master, 
          since this is consonant with reason, 
          and meritorious. 
        </p>
        <p xml:id="jsnvu6-e146938-d1e682">
          <ref xml:id="jsnvu6-e146938-Rd1e755" target="http://scta.info/resource/jsnvu6-e146938-d1e137">
            To the second argument
          </ref> 
          it must be said that the major premise is 
          false. 
          For to obey a prince in those things which pertain to such dominion 
          is necessary, 
          but to bring another to judgment 
          before an unbelieving judge is voluntary, 
          and therefore the first is obligatory 
          but the second is not, 
          but merely voluntary: 
          whence where it tends to 
          danger it is illicit, 
          in which case the Apostle speaks. 
          But 
          what the Lord says 
          <ref xml:id="jsnvu6-e146938-Rd1e771" corresp="#jsnvu6-e146938-Qd1e773">
            in Matthew 17
          </ref> 
          <quote xml:id="jsnvu6-e146938-Qd1e773" source="http://scta.info/resource/mt17_25@10-12">
            the sons are free
          </quote>
          speaking of himself, 
          he says this, 
          for he was the son of the eternal king, 
          as 
          <ref xml:id="jsnvu6-e146938-Rd1e779" corresp="#jsnvu6-e146938-Qd1e784">
            Peter had said before 
            in the sixteenth chapter
          </ref> 
          <quote xml:id="jsnvu6-e146938-Qd1e784" source="http://scta.info/resource/mt16_16@5-10">
            You are the Christ the son of the living God
          </quote>,
          and therefore he was free 
          from the obligation of tribute, 
          but it is not so with us nor was it so then 
          with the other believers of that time. 
          For the Lord commanded them 
          to pay tributes to the unbelieving prince, 
          <ref xml:id="jsnvu6-e146938-Rd1e793" corresp="#jsnvu6-e146938-Qd1e798">
            in the twenty-second chapter of Matthew
          </ref> 
          saying, 
          <quote xml:id="jsnvu6-e146938-Qd1e798" source="http://scta.info/resource/mt22_21@7-12">
            Render to Caesar the things that are Caesar's
          </quote>.
          
        </p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>